视频后续的注释部分会出现在这里，如果兴趣不大可以不用读www
Woodash 个人翻译，水平有限，欢迎反馈
如果喜欢该视频，请支持原作者
Internet Underground | The Origins of Hacker Culture
https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zBE9_kTFIro
字幕文件在这里获取：
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://github.com/WoodAsh2501/Woodash-kaorou
On January 8th, in 1986,
1986 年，1 月 8 日
a short essay titled "The Conscience of a Hacker" was shared online.
原文: http://phrack.org/issues/7/3.html
一篇题为《黑客道德》的短文被大量转发
It was written shortly after the arrest of a hacker known as The Mentor,
化名“导师”的黑客在被捕后写了这篇文章
an attempt to define the hacker ethos.
他在文中尝试定义了黑客的精神
The end of the essay states the following:
文章结尾处写道：
"We seek after knowledge,"
“我们寻求知识”
"and you call us criminals."
“你们却说我们是罪犯”
"We exist without skin color, without nationality,"
“我们不论肤色，不论国籍”
"without religious bias,"
“不论宗教异同”
"and you call us criminals."
“你们却说我们是罪犯”
"Yes, I am a criminal,"
“好 我就是罪犯”
"my crime is that of curiosity."
“我的罪孽是好奇”
"You may stop me, but you can't stop us all."
“你们可以阻止我 但不能阻止我们”
"That's cool."
“真酷”
All right, there are three different kinds:
我们继续说吧 黑客一共有三种
there's white hat - the good guys,
白帽——好人
there's gray hat - the good and bad guys,
灰帽——亦正亦邪
and then there's black hat -
然后是黑帽——
just the bad guys.
纯纯的坏人
They're comprised of coders, engineers, social engineers,
他们包括程序员、工程师、社会工程师
activists, network specialists, scammers,
活动家、网络专家、诈骗犯
crackers, and exploiters.
破解者和利用漏洞的人
Some of them work alone, some of them work in groups.
有些人独来独往 有些人抱团行动
And some of them even work for the government,
有些甚至为政府工作
I mean until they don't.
我是说——在离开之前
They're the outcasts,
他们是边缘人
the antisocial nerds,
是反社会的书呆子
the losers with computers.
是捣鼓电脑的失败者
But, they're also the ones who got rich off Bitcoin,
但 他们也是从比特币中发家致富的人
the ones who throw a crazy party in Las Vegas every year,
是每年在拉斯维加斯举办疯狂派对的人
the ones who start billion-dollar tech companies,
是创办了市值数十亿美元的科技公司的人
the ones who steal millions of dollars from those tech companies.
是从那些科技公司窃取数百万美元的人
They're the ones who have changed the world.
他们是改变了世界的人
They are the hackers.
他们就是黑客
But how did we even get here?
但 事情是怎么变成这样的？
火车模型
Our story begins right at the start of what many now call
我们的故事从这个时候开始
the culture decade.
指 20 世纪 60 年代，也被称为“反文化的年代”，与如下文化概念相关：
摇滚乐英伦入侵、新浪潮电影、嬉皮士文化、迷幻剂 / 毒品文化
新左翼、性解放、第二波女性主义运动、民权运动、反越战运动
文化年代
波士顿
20 世纪 60 年代
麻省理工学院
In the early 1960s,
在 20 世纪 60 年代早期
a rebellious and transformative culture
叛逆和变革的文化
took root within the prestigious halls of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
深深扎根在麻省理工学院显赫辉煌的大厅中
The beginning of hacker culture started on campus in Building 20,
黑客文化起源于学校里的 20 号楼
a structure which has since been deemed "The Magical Incubator".
后来人们说这座建筑是“神奇的孵化器”
Located on the third floor,
在建筑的三楼
you could find a crowded classroom that space was absolutely dominated
你可以找到一个人满为患的教室
by a carefully constructed layout of model train tracks.
精心布置的模型轨道把房间塞得满满当当
This space was the home to MIT's very own Tech Model Railroad Club.
这里就是麻省理工特有的技术模型铁路俱乐部的小窝
The club consisted of different groups that worked together
俱乐部里的小组分工合作
towards their common goal of automating the operation of model trains.
为实现模型机车的自动化控制共同奋斗
Some focused on crafting historical train replicas,
一些成员专注于复刻历史上的机车
others on scenery and buildings,
一些负责环境和建筑
but it was one group in particular,
还有一个小组很特别
the signals and power subcommittee,
叫 信号和电力小组委员会
who were responsible for first popularizing the term:
他们率先普及了下面这个术语
"hacker."
“黑客”
this group was mainly responsible for creating the circuits that operated the trains
这个小组主要负责研发火车的控制电路
they were basically the engineers behind the whole operation.
可以说 他们就是整个自动化背后的工程师
One member of the subcommittee was a guy named Peter Samson
其中有一个叫做 Peter Samson 的成员
Now it's important to understand that Peter was absolutely obsessed with electronics and automation,
重点是 Peter 对电子学和自动化很着迷
and he was always looking for new ways to be creative
而且他不断创新
and pioneer new systems, to operate model trains within the TMRC.
领导着俱乐部建立新的铁路控制系统
He was also someone who loved to explore.
他也是一个热爱探险的人
One fateful night around 2:00 in the morning,
在命运之夜的凌晨两点左右
he roamed the basement hallways of Building 26
他在 26 号楼的地下室走廊中徘徊
in search of something intriguing.
寻找有趣的东西
Little did he know that this nocturnal exploration would lead him to a discovery,
他全然不知 这次夜间探索会有所发现
propelling him into a new realm of creativity
会让他进入创造的新领域
and even the beginning of a new lifestyle.
甚至会开创一种新的生活方式
Upon entering an area that was labeled the Electronic Accounting Machinery Room,
进入标有“电子会计机房”的区域后
Peter caught his first glimpse of an IBM 704,
Peter 第一次看见了 IBM 704
a multi-million dollar mainframe that took up almost the entirety of the space.
那是一台价值百万美元的大型机 几乎塞满了整个房间
Now, Peter was definitely not supposed to be here,
可 Peter 绝对不该出现在这里
as the room was usually heavily staffed during the day,
白天房间里通常挤满了人
and only people with official security clearance from MIT, were allowed to operate the computer in the first place.
并且只有获得学校的官方安全许可的人 才能优先使用计算机
But...
但是…
no one was ever there at 2 a.m.
半夜两点根本没人在那里
Alongside other members of the TMRC,
和俱乐部的其他成员一起
Peter would regularly sneak into the basement of Building 26 at night
Peter 经常在夜里潜入 26 号楼的地下室
to use the computer and other devices held by the EAM room.
使用机房里的计算机和其他设备
These acts of defiance would mark the beginning of hacker culture as we now know it today.
这些蔑视规定的行为标志着黑客文化的诞生 我们今日再熟悉不过了
Machine time was extremely, tight.
能用机器的时间特别的 紧
Uh...
额…
They found times in the middle of the night,
他们发现半夜是个好时机
maybe in unlocked computer rooms where they could do these things.
可以潜入没上锁的机房做些事情
The liberal arts majors, who
那些文科专业的学生
whose only computer time available was if they
他们唯一能用电脑的方式就是
gummed up the locks and sneak into the building late at night
深夜里用口香糖撬锁然后偷偷溜进室内
because they weren't allowed to sign up for this stuff
因为他们没有资格申请使用电脑
The people that took a systematic approach toward the development of uh computer software
那些系统地学习计算机软件开发的人
missed the boat.
错失了天大的良机
It was a trial and error (for) people working illegally, in the underground
*没听明白（？
那些违规的人在地下室不断试验
This move made most (of) the advances.
导致他们遥遥领先于学院派
In the following years, the TMRC would continue tinkering with computer technology
接下来的几年里 俱乐部会继续钻研计算机技术
whether they had permission or not.
无论他们有没有许可
But to be honest,
但老实说
using model trains as your excuse to be a hacker,
打着火车模型的幌子当黑客
could really only get you so far.
最多也只能做这些事了
Subsequently, many TMRC members that were a part of the Signals and Power Subcommittee
后来 许多参加小组委员会的俱乐部成员
went on to join MIT's Artificial Intelligence Lab.
加入了麻省理工人工智能实验室
Led by the MIT Lab Director Marvin Minsky,
在实验室主任 Marvin Minsky 的指引中
these early hackers had found a supportive mentor.
这些早期黑客发现他是一位很支持他们的导师
Impressed by their determination, Minsky allowed them direct access to the machines.
Minsky 被他们的决心深深打动 允许他们直接使用机器
And with that, the lab members went to work.
就这样，实验室成员开始工作了
Among the many achievements of the MIT AI Lab
麻省理工学院人工智能实验室有着诸多成就
was the creation of Spacewar!,
其中就有《太空大战！》
one of the first video games predating Pong by a decade.
《乓》是 Atari 公司于 1972 年发布的街机游戏，支持二人对战
这是“乒乓”的“乓”字
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pong
这是最早的电子游戏之一，比《乓》早了十年
"So those stars is a part from Peter Samson wrote called Expensive Planetarium."
昂贵天文馆是一个基于真实星图的程序，包括 22.5° N 到 22.5° S 中的所有亮于 5 视星等的恒星
昂贵是说运行代码的 PDP-1 计算机比用投影仪的传统天文馆贵
PDP-1 在当时的价格为 12 万美元，等价于 2024 年 8 月的 125 万美元，换算为 898 万人民币
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spacewar!
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDP-1
“这些星星是 Peter Samson 写的‘昂贵天文馆’里的一部分”
"And it's ..." (Laugh)
“它……”（笑声）
With the success of visionaries at MIT,
随着学校里那些远见人士的成功
and as the 1960s unfolded,
以及 20 世纪 60 年代的到来
the hacker ethos began to spread like wildfire,
黑客思潮如野火一样蔓延
igniting centers of innovation at universities across the nation.
引燃了全美大学的创新中心
From Carnegie Mellon to Stanford, the spirit of exploration thrived,
探索精神在卡内基梅隆和斯坦福这些学校里蓬勃发展
fostering a new breed of technological pioneers.
培养出了新一代的技术先锋
At this point, hacker culture seemed to be quite contained to the more academic circles,
此时 黑客文化似乎还更多地局限于学术界
and it actually seemed like it was going to stay that way for a while.
这种情况看上去好像还会持续一段时间
But it wasn't long until hacking spawned the comp-sci student dropout cliché, that we know all too well today.
Steve Jobs
Michael Dell
Bill Gates
Mark Zuckerberg
Larry Ellison (1)
Larry Ellison (2nd.)
严格来说真正的计科辍学并不是很多，不过扩展到计算机行业的不完全统计如下：
苹果·　　　　　　　　　　 - 1 学期，里德学院，英语专业
戴尔·　　　　　　　　　　 - 2 学期，得克萨斯大学奥斯汀分校，医学预科
微软·　　　　　　　　　　 - 3 学期，哈佛大学，在选专业前退学，学了数学和计算机的课程
脸书·　　　　　　　　　　 - 4 学期，哈佛大学，计算机科学与心理学
甲骨文·　　　　　　　　　 - 4 学期，伊利诺伊大学厄巴纳-尚佩恩分校，医学预科
- 1 学期，芝加哥大学，物理学与数学
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jobs
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Dell
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Gates
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Zuckerberg
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry_Ellison
但再过不久 黑客文化就会催生出我们熟知的典中典之计科辍学了
It all starts
一切
with the telephone.
都从电话开始
飞客和极客
"You know, Steve was never like you or me,"
“你也知道，Steve Jobs 从不会像你和我一样”
"he always saw things differently."
“他总是视角不同”
不同凡想
"Steve and I found this weird guy who was a hero around Berkeley,"
“Steve 和我发现了这个怪人 他也是整个伯克利的英雄”
"all because he found a way to beat the system."
“这么说是因为他找到了战胜系统的办法”
"This guy was called Captain Crunch"
“这个人叫脆脆船长”
"because he figured out,"
“因为他发现”
"this little whistle that you found in boxes of Cap'n Crunch cereal"
Cap'n Crunch: 一个谷物品牌，主要产品有麦片、燕麦、脆饼等
此词翻译引用自南方公园中文维基
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://south-park.fandom.com/zh/wiki/脆脆船长
“在脆脆船长麦片包装盒中找到的这个小哨子”
"had the same tones as AT&T's long-distance equipment."
AT&T: 美国最大的电话电信公司，前身是贝尔电话公司
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AT&T
“和 AT&T 的远距离通信设备有着一样的声音”
"So you got free phone calls anywhere in the world, with with this thing I built called the blue box."
“所以你无论在哪里都可以免费打电话 用上我做的这个蓝盒子就行”
"And then we tested it out by calling the Pope."
Wozniak当时假冒美国国务卿 Henry Kissinger，代时任美国总统 Richard Nixon 打电话给罗马教宗
当时教宗正在休息，随后他也被揭穿了
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Wozniak
“然后我们打电话给罗马教宗测试了一下”
"You talk."
“你说两句”
"No, no, they're not putting you through to the Pope, are they?"
“不对 他们没把电话给教宗吧？没给吧？”
There was a huge culture shift when John Draper, also known as Captain Crunch,
脆脆船长 John Draper 给黑客文化带来了巨大的转变
helped pioneer the world of phone phreaking
他打开了“电话飞客”的新世界大门
电话飞客
By blowing into that toy whistle.
吹吹玩具哨子
*beep
*哔—
Draper and countless others fooled the phone company,
Draper 和一大群人就骗过了电话公司
and made free calls all around the world.
在世界各地免费打电话
When the two Steves began developing and distributing the aforementioned blue boxes,
two Steves: 指 Steve Wozniak 和 Steve Jobs，二人都是苹果公司的创办者
Jobs 和 Wozniak 二人开始制造并派发之前说的蓝盒子的时候
it actually marked one of the first times hacker culture garnered attention from the mainstream media.
黑客文化第一次受到主流媒体的关注
When Esquire magazine wrote about it in a 1971 article,
《时尚先生》杂志在 1971 年写了一篇文章介绍这件事情
released in the same year.
在那一年
Freaking was also covered prominently in Abby Hoffman's now infamous publication,
Abby Hoffman 那本如今臭名昭著的书也特别介绍了如何当飞客
"Steal This Book."
Steal This Book: 反主流文化的标志性书籍，是一本指导如何不择手段地反抗政府与公司的青年指南。
“生存”部分介绍了如何免费或者低价获取生活资料，也包括乞讨、商店行窃等
“战斗”部分介绍了如何创办地下报刊与电台，非暴力示威，如何制作自制炸弹，游击战等
“解放”部分介绍了纽约、芝加哥、洛杉矶和旧金山四个城市的信息
附录中记载了支持的组织和其他“值得偷的书”
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steal_This_Book
那本书叫《偷走这本书》
Now to be clear, freaking wasn't just about making free calls,
需要澄清的是 飞客行为并不仅仅是为了免费打电话
not to the hackers back then at least.
至少对于那时的黑客不是这样
Freaking was a new way to learn how the phone network worked,
当飞客意味着用新方式学习电话网络工作原理
a way to pull some harmless pranks,
做些无害的恶作剧
a way to build a community within a growing subculture,
在成长中的亚文化里建立社群
and in some cases,
有些情况下
a way to just simply stick it to the man.
就是单纯地找茬
Honestly, it can be argued that freaking turned out to be
坦然地讲 即使不说飞客的影响最为深远
one of, if not the most influential aspects of hacker culture we've seen to date.
那也是如今黑客文化极具影响力的一个侧面了
With Steve Jobs even going as far as to say that,
Steve Jobs 甚至这么说过
"if it had not been for Wozniak's blue boxes,"
“如果没有 Wozniak 做的蓝盒子”
"there wouldn't have been an Apple."
“就不会有苹果公司了”
This isn't the last time freaking will come up in this video,
之后我们还会谈到飞客
as it definitely continued to evolve over the years.
因为这么多年来它确实一直在发展
But for now,
不过呢
let's go back to the topic of computers.
现在还是回到计算机的话题吧
"What's the mail this morning?"
“今早有什么邮件？”
"This one looks interesting, let's uh take a look at this."
“这个看上去很有趣 我们看看吧”
"I'm going to need a couple of copies of this."
“我需要几份这个文件的拷贝”
"You'll have a television screen like this here, and a keyboard."
“你的电脑会有一个这样的电视屏幕 和一个键盘”
"And you'll talk to the computer, get information from it,"
“然后你可以和电脑交流来获取一些信息”
"and you'll take it as much for granted as we take the telephone."
“你会觉得这种行为理所当然 就像接电话一样”
"I wonder that what sort of a life would it be like in social terms?"
“我好奇的是 从社会角度来看 那种生活是怎样的？”
"Their whole life is built around the computer."
“他们的生活全都围绕着电脑”
"Do we become a computer-dependent society?"
“我们会变成一个电脑依赖型社会吗？”
"In some ways, but they eh would also enrich our society,"
“某种程度上可以这么说 但电脑也会丰富我们的社会”
"and this is a wonderful thing."
“这是一件很棒的事情”
As the 1970s progressed,
随着 20 世纪 70 年代到来
so did the interconnectedness of computer networks.
计算机网络相互连接在了一起
The rise of ARPANET provided a new frontier for exploration and experimentation.
阿帕网的兴起为探索和实验提供了新的领域
I'll try not to bore you, but for those unfamiliar,
我尽量不说得太枯燥 但还是为那些不熟悉的人介绍一下
ARPANET was a computer network that helped lay the groundwork for the modern Internet.
阿帕网是一种计算机网络 奠定了现代互联网的基础
It started out in the late '60s,
它在 60 年代后期发明
mostly being used by research institutions and government agencies.
基本都是研究机构和政府部门在使用
Along the way, it helped define how file sharing works
阿帕网在发展中定义了文件共享的方式
and was even used to send and receive the first email.
甚至被用来收发第一封电子邮件
The network was pretty small initially,
阿帕网一开始的规模很小
but as it grew, it quickly became a playground for hackers
但随着规模扩大 它很快变成了黑客的游乐场
eager to push the boundaries of technology and communication.
他们渴望推动技术和通讯的发展
ARPANET also just happened to be
阿帕网也正正好好
the first computer network to get infected.
成为了第一个被感染的计算机网络
In 1971, a computer scientist by the name of Bob Thomas created what is widely accepted as the first computer virus,
1971 年 一位叫 Bob Thomas 的计算机科学家发明了公认的第一种计算机病毒
now known as the Creeper virus.
Creeper: 释义注重古怪、鬼祟与令人毛骨悚然，而直译的“爬行者”一词并无此倾向
查询到艺术创作中 Creeper 与《巴黎圣母院》中 Quasimodo 的形象具有相似处
仿照台译版“钟楼怪人”，译为“佝偻怪人”
迪士尼相关百科页面中提及 Creeper (The Black Cauldron) 的早期概念形象看起来像 Quasimodo；使用搜索引擎并列搜索二词亦有相关联想
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://disney.fandom.com/wiki/Creeper/Gallery
现在称其为“佝偻怪人”病毒
This computer worm replicated itself and spread to other systems using ARPANET.
这个蠕虫病毒会自我复制 并通过阿帕网传染到其他电脑中
It was developed by Bob while working at a technology research firm,
病毒是 Bob 在科研公司工作时开发的
and unlike most viruses,
和大多数的病毒不一样
it wasn't made with any malicious intent.
它并没有任何恶意目的
The virus didn't cause any damage to your system,
这个病毒不会损害你的系统
but instead displayed a message:
只会显示一条信息
我是佝偻的怪人 有本事就来抓我
It's actually kind of funny.
这其实有点好笑
Because this playful yet disruptive act
因为这种找了乐子惹了麻烦的行为
foreshadowed the cat and mouse game between hackers and security professionals that continues to this day.
预示了黑客和安全专家之间持续至今的猫鼠游戏
The 1970s marked a turning point, as hackers began to forge their own identity and beliefs.
20 世纪 70 年代是黑客们形成身份认同和信仰的转折点
Rumblings of what would become known as the free software movement began to circulate.
人们开始口耳相传 聊些我们后来称为“自由软件运动”的事情
Essential books that shaped hacker culture were published.
很多塑造了黑客文化的书也出版了
The decade even saw the emergence of something called the Jargon File,
在这十年里甚至出现了叫做“黑话文档”的东西
which acted as a dictionary of slang used by hackers and computer programmers.
就是黑客和程序员的俚语词典
It was things like this that further solidified the community's shared language and values.
正是这种东西进一步巩固了社群的共同语言和价值观
However, the one thing the culture lacked during this moment in time
然而 此时整个文化社群还缺少一个东西
was a central meeting ground.
一个聚会中心
Sure, ARPANET existed.
确实 当时已经有阿帕网了
But again, it was usually restricted to institutions funded by the US government.
但梅开二度 网络通常只有美国政府资助的机构才能使用
Local meet-ups like The Homebrew Computer Club offered some networking opportunities,
Homebrew Computer Club: Jobs 和 Wozniak 等人参与的计算机爱好者团体
私酿的概念来源于美国 20 世纪 20 年代的禁酒令
官方认定酒为非法产品，然而人们发现酿酒的材料是合法的
于是美国家庭购买原料并在家中制造私酿酒
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homebrew_Computer_Club
(CC-BY-SA 4.0) https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homebrewing
像“私酿计算机俱乐部”这样的线下聚会提供了一些上网的机会
but their accessibility was limited only to those who could physically attend.
但也只有能亲自参加聚会的人才可以接入网络
The good news was, it wouldn't take too long to fill this cultural void.
好消息是 再过不久这块空白就被填上了
In 1978,
1978 年
two guys from Chicago developed something called computer bulletin board systems,
芝加哥来的两个人开发了一种叫做“
计算机布告栏系统
”的东西
BBS
serving as the first virtual meeting place for early hackers.
用以充当早期黑客的第一个虚拟聚会场所
BBS allowed users to dial in with their modems,
用户可以用
调制解调器
接入 BBS
光猫
exchange messages, share software, and participate in discussions,
交换信息、共享软件、参与讨论
laying the groundwork for the incoming rise of the hacker groups.
这为即将流行的黑客小组奠定了基础
感谢收看！请期待下一集！